I guess you're real.
All right, it's 1030 so we'll
get started.
Hope everyone enjoyed the long
weekend.
Announcements as far as our
class goes,
one,
homework one is due on Friday
including the welcome survey.
Try and fill out the welcome
survey sooner than that.
I've been reaching out to some
of the other instructors that
people have said they have
midterm conflicts with and like
the sooner you let us know about
that stuff the better.
Office hours are usually after
lecture including today and if
you take a look at the schedule
you'll see that I've added a few
remote office hours throughout
the week I've just so you can
check in with me if you need to
and aren't able to come to any
of the others but keep checking
the schedule because we will
tweak the office hours schedule
week to week and then finally
lab 2 is tomorrow and remember
attendance is part of your
grade.
Speaking of attendance and you
know lecture attendance is part
of your grade as well.
Sometime next week, I will give
you this portal where you can go
and check your attendance for
all of the lectures and labs.
And that's where we will also
show you your grades on things
like homeworks and eventually
exams as well.
So that's coming in just a
little bit.
The plan for today is to start
by recapping the big idea we
finished Thursday's lecture
with,
that of the modeling recipe.
We will make sure we understand
what that was all about.
We will formally introduce this
term empirical risk, which we've
briefly mentioned already.
And then spend a little bit of
time thinking about how
everything we did last week
would have changed if we instead
of using squared loss, which was
the loss function we chose,
used other loss functions like
absolute loss or something you
will see in lab tomorrow,
zero one loss or infinity loss.
Like, these are all possible
loss functions one could use,
and they have different effects
on the resulting predictions.
And then, with maybe five or 10
minutes at the very end, we will
briefly introduce the idea of
the simple linear regression
model.
And you will play around with
that more in lab tomorrow.
And then Thursday's lecture will
be all about that.
OK, any logistical questions
with where we are in the class
right now?
All good?
OK,
so what was the point of both of
our lectures
last week? What were we building
towards?
What were we trying to do?
In our lectures last week,
what were we trying to do, and
what does this graph have to do
with it?
Yes,
Allison.
Last lecture specifically, we
were trying to find the best
place to put our pasta.
Exactly.
That was our sole focus of last
lecture.
Where is the best
place to
place this flat line
for predicting commute
time.
Remember the whole idea here was
that we've collected this data
set of on the x-axis the time we
left in the morning for work and
on the y-axis how long it
actually took to get to work in
minutes as a function of the
time we left and the goal was to
build a function called the
hypothesis function that allows
us to predict how long it's
going to take for us to get to
work tomorrow or some other day,
depending on the time we leave
in the morning.
And the first model we chose,
the constant model,
said it wasn't even going to use
the time we left in the morning.
It was just going to predict the
same constant.
I can see here, I kind of didn't
do the best job of drawing a
totally flat line.
That's better.
the constant model says we're
not going to use the time we
leave in the morning at all,
we're just going to make the
same prediction regardless of
the time we leave in the
morning.
So a constant model looks like
this flat line and then the
question was where was the best
place to draw that flat line?
What is the best constant to
predict?
And to do that, we implicitly
introduced what we call the
three-step modeling recipe.
And this is something I defined
at the very end of Thursday's
class.
Can someone remind me what those
three steps were?
choose model choose loss
function and then minimize the
average loss to find W.
Awesome the three steps were
first choose a model the second
choose a loss function and third
minimize average loss
to find
optimal parameters.
Okay so what So that was the
model we chose,
as we've already stated,
we chose the constant model,
whose equation looks like h of
xi equals
w.
w is our one parameter here.
It is the one thing we have
control over.
OK.
The second stage involved us
choosing the squared loss
function.
Can someone remind me what the
point of a loss function is?
Jovan.
Optimal like w?
That's the point of this whole
thing in general.
Yeah.
So you have the right idea.
But what does a loss function
specifically do?
Maaj.
Find the error?
Yeah,
what the loss function is doing
is it's telling us how we want
to measure for one data point
how good or bad the prediction
was.
So a loss function is about
measuring error for one data
point,
and then average loss averages
that measurement across the
whole data set, because we want
predictions that are good on
average for our whole data set.
So, recall,
the formula for the squared loss
function looked something like
L subscript S Q
and it took in two arguments.
Those arguments were the actual
y value,
y i,
and the predicted y value h of
xi.
And what does it return?
It returns their difference
squared.
All this is saying is find the
squared difference between my
actual y value and my predicted
y value.
Now, in the case of the constant
model,
anywhere you see this h of xi,
you plug in a w.
Because the constant model, its
predictions
are just the one constant
parameter,
w.
But later today and on Thursday,
when we look at more complicated
models,
the h of xi you see on the right
is going to be substituted in
with something more complicated,
which makes the process of
finding optimal parameters,
in those cases,
more complicated as well.
Okay,
so I want to talk a little bit
more about that third step,
average loss.
So
the function that
we minimized
looked
like this.
And it was average loss when
using the
results of the first two steps
of the three step process, which
is once you've chosen the
constant model
and squared loss,
then this is what average loss
looks like.
The impact of choosing the
constant model
is that we just have that single
w here.
But if we were looking at
average loss for the simple
linear regression model or some
other more complicated model,
well, then this wouldn't just be
a w.
It would be something more
complicated.
There are a few names for this
function.
What were a few things we could
call this?
What's up?
Mean squared error.
Yeah, mean squared error.
Good.
What were some other names?
Gavin.
Empirical risk.
Good.
What was it? There was one other
name.
The other thing was average
squared loss.
I'll actually leave empirical
risk off of here for now because
it's a more general term which
I'm about to define but average
squared loss mean squared error
both refer to this thing okay
and what did we find was the
optimal W?
What did we find was the optimal
W?
Yeah it Yeah, it was the
average,
or mean,
of the y's.
And this star here means that
it's an optimal parameter.
So what that tells us, going
back to this picture from two
slides ago, was that we
discovered with all of this math
last class that the optimal
place to draw this flat line was
at the average of all of the y
values.
OK?
Questions so far?
And like I said, last class,
we minimized this function
how?
What was the technique we used
for minimizing it to find the
optimal Ws.
Alex.
You can be derivative and then
we can solve,
I guess.
Yeah, what we did is we used
tools from calc 1, where we took
its derivative, set that equal
to 0,
and solved.
What you're doing in homework 1
is another technique for
minimizing this function.
OK, and what we saw is that it
looks like a parabola.
It is a quadratic in terms of
the Ws.
Remember, there are lots of
symbols on the right-hand side,
but the only unknown is double.
The y's are treated as something
that is given to you.
So I've said this before,
but here's where I want to
define it.
Empirical risk is just a fancy
term for average loss.
OK,
and what does the term empirical
mean? I should have commented on
this last week when I first said
this.
What does empirical mean?
You may have heard of this
before.
Yeah,
through, right?
Yes, observed.
Yeah,
it's like observed or like comes
from
real data.
What's the opposite of
empirical?
Yeah?
Theoretical.
Theoretical,
right? And this is maybe
something like a distinction you
learned about in a high school
science class, right?
So empirical risk just means it
is the risk, which I'm about to
define,
measured using real data, the
data set of X's and Y's we
collected.
What is theoretical risk?
It's not something we're going
to study much in this class, but
theoretical risk Risk is an idea
that you study if you take like
a 400 level statistics class.
And there,
with theoretical risk, or just
risk,
what you try and measure is the
average squared loss across all
theoretical possible data sets
you could come across from a
particular distribution,
like all theoretical commute
times.
But in order to measure that,
you would need to have a precise
probability model that describes
what the distribution of commute
times looks like, for example.
But that's not something we're
going to get into in this class.
Just know that that's what risk
is meant to be, like the average
expected loss.
Empirical risk means we are
computing this using the data we
actually have.
The reason I'm introducing this
term
because empirical risk
minimization is the
like industry standard term for
the three-step modeling recipe.
So I called it this three-step
thing where you choose a model
loss function and minimize
average loss.
In future classes like when when
you take EECS 445 they will just
call all of that empirical risk
minimization.
Which is why when you go back
here,
yes,
it's true that you can call this
function
R of w equals the sum of yi
minus w squared, all divided by
n.
You can call this empirical
risk,
but using squared loss,
because when I change the loss
function,
and it is still empirical risk.
Now to give you a sense of
what this all means,
what I want you to do is I'm
going to give you a new loss
function,
one that you haven't seen
before.
And this is the type of question
you're going to see in
tomorrow's lab and in homework
two.
And what I want you to do is
find And the optimal w,
the optimal model parameter,
that minimizes empirical risk
for this new
loss function.
So let's come up with the new
loss function,
L,
I don't know,
Western Michigan,
OK, sure.
First thing that came to mind.
And instead of returning yi
minus h of xi squared,
I'm going to have a return for
yi minus three h of xi
squared.
And my question is,
for this new loss function
and the constant
model,
which again has the formula
we've seen,
h of xi equals w.
Find the optimal
parameter,
w star
Minimizes average WM,
Western Michigan, loss.
And average whatever loss is
referred to by empirical risk.
Is the question clear? What I'm
looking for is a new formula for
a w star.
It is not going to be the same
as the mean of the y.
But it will be related to the
mean of the y's, maybe.
One would expect that it should
be related because it still
looks like something minus
something else squared.
But it's more complicated than
that because we have this 4 and
this 3.
So what I want you to do is take
out a pen and paper
and see if you can find the new
optimal parameter
under this new loss function.
And I'll give you a few minutes
to do this.
And I'll walk around to help if
you have any questions.
Feel free to flag me down if
there's anything I can help
with.
Sorry,
where'd you get it?
Where'd you get
it?
And what I'll say is, in this
specific case,
there's both an easy way to do
it and a hard way.
And when we take it up, we'll
start with the harder way
and then maybe look at the
easier way.
Okay, we can start to take it
up, but if you're still working
on it, please feel free.
The first thing we need to do in
my mind
is write out the formula of the
actual function we want to
minimize.
So this is our new loss
function.
But here,
we're using the constant model.
So we should use the fact that h
of xi equals w.
So what is the actual function
we want to minimize?
The function that we're actually
going to minimize, guys, what
does it look like?
Gavin.
RWM is 1 over n
times the sum from i equals 1 to
n
of our loss function.
4yi minus 3w squared.
Do we agree?
And then the one input to this
function is w.
So, one thing we could do is
take the derivative of this,
set it equal to zero, and solve,
and we can do that really
quickly.
I will go through this a little
more quickly than we did on
Thursday,
but I'll still do because it's
useful to review.
One of the key ideas we looked
at on Thursday was that the
derivative of a sum is equal to
the sum of the things,
sorry, the sum of the
derivatives of the individual
terms.
And the 1 over n constant factor
just comes along for the ride.
So the derivative of this
function that we are minimizing,
which is our empirical risk or
our average loss,
should write that down,
is 1 over n times the sum,
again, from i equals 1 to n, of
what?
What goes out here?
What comes here?
Gavin.
You can use the power rule.
Good.
Take the squared out and make
the coefficient.
So it would be 2 times 4y of i
minus 3w
times
would be negative 3.
Good
Okay So first we use the power
rule that which says the
derivative of box squared is
equal to 2 times box But then
the chain rule says you have to
follow that up with the
derivative of whatever is in the
box here with respect to W and
the derivative of 4 y I minus 3
W with respect to W is Negative
3 because the coefficient on W
is negative 3 What this means is
that we have a constant factor
of 2 times negative 3 which is
negative six that can be pulled
up front,
times the sum of
four yi minus three w.
Now this is the derivative of
average loss.
Now what we need to do is set
this equal to zero and solve for
the w that accomplishes that.
Do we agree?
All on the same page?
So this looks a lot like the
derivative of of mean squared
error we saw last class, it's
just that there,
there was no 4 here and no 3
here.
So the question is,
how do those change the
resulting optimal w?
Well,
like we did last class, we can
multiply both sides by negative
n over 6 to get rid of this
constant factor.
It doesn't really contribute
anything.
But that doesn't mean the 4s and
3s in here
can get multiplied out.
Those still stick around.
We can't really get rid of
those.
It's just a thing outside of the
summation we can multiply out
by.
What I'll do now is expand this
into the sum of 4yi
minus the sum of 3w, using and
the fact that I
can separate sums.
Where do I go from here?
The sum of 4yi minus the sum of
3w.
Both sums are from i equals 1 to
n.
Alex?
You can simplify the second sum
with just negative 3wn.
Good.
So one of the things we
discovered last class and that
you've seen in last week's lab
is that when you have a sum of a
thing that But as a constant,
all that is is really just the
constant multiplied by the
number of times the sum runs, or
the number of terms in the sum,
which is n.
So the second piece is just 3wn.
Do we agree with that?
OK, and the first piece,
I can simplify this a little
bit.
How can I do that?
Move the 4 out of the summation.
Yeah, so tell me the first
letter of your name again.
Is it also Alex?
Andrew?
Yes.
OK, good.
We can pull the 4 out.
And now,
all we have to do is isolate for
w.
So let me come over here.
Maybe I can say 3wn
is equal to 4 times the sum of
my yi's.
And lastly, all I need to do is
divide both sides here by 3n.
What that gives me is w on the
left,
which now that I've isolated for
it, I'll call it w star, Is four
times the sum of my y's
Over 3n
but
This really just looks like 4
over 3 times
the sum of the y's over n
So is there a simpler way I can
write this
Yes, and remind me of your name
again.
Gustavo.
Gustavo, right?
Yes, exactly.
It's just four thirds
times y bar,
OK?
Now,
this is a good fallback to
always have.
When in doubt,
this technique will work.
And for the questions you will
see in tomorrow's lab and
homework two, you're going to
need to follow these steps,
OK?
Now, those questions will not
have loss functions that
essentially look like squared
loss with one tiny change,
they'll have more substantial
changes.
So you will walk through these
calculus steps, and you'll end
up with a formula that doesn't
involve the mean.
You'll find some other thing.
Like, for example,
this is maybe giving away the
answer, but you still have to
work through all the math.
Remember,
in last week's lab,
we introduced this thing called
the harmonic mean, which is like
how you found the average of a
bunch of speeds.
You remember this?
The first question in tomorrow's
lab will give you a new loss
function, and the optimal w will
end up being the harmonic mean
of the y values, okay? But the
last function looks more,
not more complicated
necessarily, but it doesn't look
like sort of a rebadged version
of square loss.
It looks a little different.
Okay,
but knowing that this is how the
answer turned out,
can you think of an easier way
to minimize
this function?
like maybe leveraging things we
already knew,
knowing that the optimal w ends
up being 4 over 3
times the mean of the y's, could
we have arrived at this
differently, like in a quicker
way?
I'll give you a hint.
Think about if you took calc 2,
you learned about this technique
that they used a lot for finding
complicated integrals?
What was that technique called?
Yeah, u-substitution.
Can we invent some new variables
here that allow us to use the
main result we already knew
about on Thursday and already
recapped today?
Which is that if there wasn't a
4 here and wasn't a 3 here, and
this was just yi minus w
squared,
we wouldn't need to do any
calculation.
We already know that the optimal
w is just the mean.
So maybe what we can do is
introduce some new variables
so that there aren't
coefficients here
and work backwards to figure out
what the impact of the 3 and 4
should be.
Let me give you a rundown of
what I mean.
Let's define two new variables.
So let's define a zi that is
equal to 4yi.
And why don't we define a t that
is equal to 3w?
Let's just try it.
Now,
instead of minimizing 1 over n
times the sum of 4yi
minus 3w squared,
I'm minimizing 1 over n times
the sum of zi minus
t squared.
If I do that,
what is the optimal t?
This just looks like average
squared loss or mean squared
error.
Just the variables have
different names, but that
shouldn't change the underlying
math.
If this formula or this
expression,
1 over n times the sum of zi
minus t squared,
if that's all you had,
what would you say the optimal t
is?
The average of zi.
Yeah, it would be the average of
the z's.
Do we agree with that?
But what is the average of the
z's relative to y?
Remember, I made the z's by
multiplying each y by 4.
So what should the average z be?
And yes, remind me of your name?
Chin my.
Chin my, right, yeah.
It should be 4 times the average
of the y's.
Yeah, it should just be 4 times
the average of the y's.
And this is the kind of property
you will explore in homeworks
and labs, where if you multiply
every value by a constant, And
the mean also gets multiplied by
that same constant.
OK?
So the optimal t is 4 times the
average y.
But what is the relationship
between t and w?
Well, t is equal to 3w.
So that means 3 times the
optimal w should be 4 times the
average y.
So the optimal w should be 4
over 3 times the average y.
And we arrived at this without
needing to re-derive of the
result.
And that's because we were able
to reduce the problem to one
that looked like something we've
seen before.
And this didn't require any
further assumptions on what the
y values were.
It doesn't matter what the y
values were.
This would have still worked.
Sound reasonable?
Paul.
How did you get the optimal T is
at the average Z
on the fourth line?
What I did was I asked, well,
Well, if this is all I gave you,
and you forgot about anything to
do with substitution, and I just
said,
what is the t that minimizes
this expression,
I know it is the average of the
z's, because that's what we
found last class in recap today.
This is just a rebadged version
of having y's here and a w here.
It's just with differences.
Is that clear?
Yeah.
Yeah, good.
OK,
questions otherwise with this
activity?
Yeah? So I just minimized the
loss function directly and got
the same result.
But is that just a coincidence?
So I'm glad you brought that up.
We never minimize,
at least using the terminology
in this class, we never minimize
a loss function.
Because loss measures error for
one data point.
For one data point, you can
always have zero loss if your
model goes through it.
What we always minimize is
average loss.
So you will know you're on the
right track if the derivative
that you're setting equal to 0
has a summation in it.
If it doesn't, then something is
wrong.
The ending result that you find
should involve your entire data
set.
That's true now for the constant
model and will also be true when
we look at the simple linear
regression model.
Your formulas for your optimal
parameters should involve the
whole data set.
It shouldn't just have a single
yi in it.
Because intuitively,
the optimal parameters should
have, you have to look at the
whole data set to figure out
what those are.
OK.
What I want to do now is
consider what would happen
if we run through our three-step
modeling recipe,
but start making different
choices.
And I guess we saw a little bit
of that with this activity, but
I want to choose something that
isn't sort of like squared loss.
I want to choose something
that's totally different.
So I want to pick the constant
model,
h of xi equals w.
But my loss function, I want to
use absolute loss.
Which is going to look like
L of yi comma h of xi
is the absolute difference.
No squaring here.
And so the function I am
minimizing
now
looks like this.
So,
what are some names I would call
this function?
What are some names I would call
Bella.
Sorry.
Average absolute loss.
Yeah.
I can call this average absolute
loss.
I can also call it mean absolute
error.
And because it is the average of
a loss function,
it can be called empirical risk.
Empirical risk is like a
catch-all term.
Any average of a loss function
is empirical risk.
So now the question is, suppose
we've changed our metric for how
we are measuring the quality of
a prediction.
Before,
at that step, we chose squared
loss, actual minus predicted
squared.
Now we have absolute loss, which
is just the absolute difference
between actual and predicted.
What will the optimal constant
parameter w be now?
Now I told you this at the end
of Thursday's class, but I want
us to think about why it's going
to be something different.
What is the shape of this
function?
The shape of this function,
that That is, to be clear,
average absolute loss or mean
absolute error,
this one that I'm circling here.
What does it look like if I had
to graph it out?
It would be like a V.
Yeah,
well,
it will be made up of lots of
individual Vs.
But that means the overall
result is actually a piecewise
linear function.
So this graph, even though the
formula looks more or less the
same as the formula for mean
squared error just without the
squared,
the graph itself looks much more
complicated,
okay?
And to be clear, the graph I'm
asking about is the equivalent
of the one earlier, which was a
parabola,
okay?
When we had mean squared error,
this entire expression I'm
circling looked like a parabola.
It is true that a single
absolute value function looks
like a V.
That is true.
But this is not a single
absolute value function.
This is the sum of n absolute
value functions, each of which
have their bend at a different
location.
The bends are where all of the
data points are, where the yi is
equal to the w.
So what that means is the graph
we end up with looks
something like this.
It's hard to predict what this
is going to look like,
or not hard to predict, but hard
to anticipate.
Here I'm using the same example
data set of five points
that we played around with on
Thursday,
62,
sorry, 72,
90,
61,
85,
and 92.
And what you should notice is
that exactly those five points,
this graph bends.
So do we see what I mean by this
being a piecewise linear
function?
It is broken up into how many
line segments?
How many line segments are there
here?
Yes, and remind me of your name?
Oh,
yeah.
Olam.
Five.
Close.
It's almost five.
Six.
Because there are five bends.
So factoring in whatever is to
the left of the first bend and
whatever is to the right of the
last bend,
there are six segments here.
OK.
Now,
where do you notice this graph
is at its minimizer?
Gustavo? On the median.
It is at the median.
But note that the technique for
finding that the median is the
minimizer can't involve taking
the derivative and setting it
equal to 0.
Because at all of these bends,
the derivative is undefined.
So minimizer isn't always the
same as derivative equals 0.
One of the ideas you may have
learned in calculus is that a
critical point, which is a place
where a minimizer or maximizer
could be, is anywhere where the
derivative is zero or undefined.
And the way that I think about
it is that at the bottom is
where the slope goes from
negative to positive.
So if you look at the segment to
the left of the median,
the line is decreasing, and to
the right it is increasing.
And if you think about that
conceptually,
what that means is you must be
coming out of a hole
or of a valley.
Now,
I'm intentionally not walking
through the entire derivation
for why the median minimizes
mean absolute error here,
because I want you to go and
look at the course notes for
more details.
I'm trying to give you an
intuitive understanding for why
that's the case.
But in just a little bit, I'm
going to show you a formula for
the slope of this piecewise
linear function at any value of
w.
But that function that tells me
the slope of this function
is going to have some inputs
where you can't use it,
some inputs where its behavior
is not defined.
And what are those inputs?
Like, when can I not use this
slope function?
Allison.
Will we be at the data points?
Yeah, at the w's themselves,
there is no slope.
So the function that tells you
the slope of this graph
can't work at any of the actual
data points.
OK.
Before I do that, though,
here's a question.
There were an odd number of data
points here.
So visually, we see that there
is just one minimizer.
What do you think would happen
if there were an even number of
data points?
Paul Anne?
Between the two media?
Yeah,
good intuition.
Check it out.
Now I've added a sixth data
point.
So I'm using the same five as
before,
72, 90, 61,
85 and 92.
But I've added another one, 78.
OK,
and what you see is that now
there is actually a region where
the slope is 0.
And what you see is that the
minimizer,
my optimal w,
is no longer unique.
There are actually infinitely
many w's that minimize mean
absolute error here.
What this is already telling you
is that, in general,
depending on which model and
loss function you choose, there
isn't necessarily an optimal
parameter.
There could be multiple that all
perform equally well.
And this is something that we
will see repeatedly throughout
the semester, especially when we
get to more complicated linear
algebra operations.
Questions so far?
OK,
now,
yeah, hold on.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
What would happen if one of the
mediums change a little?
Would it lower the selection?
So your question is,
what if I change one of the data
points, like I change 61 to 60
or something? Yeah,
instead of 85, let's change it
to 80.
It's still um, you know, yeah,
okay.
So instead of 85 what if I have
80 instead? Let me draw it here.
So folks over there can see So
what are the weird things about
this classroom? Like I like
pointing at the board but if I
do that here only half the
people can see so I have to
Stick to the iPad a little more
So all I'm question is what if
instead of 85 this data like we
move the 85 to here
And then we would just have a
smaller thing here
And it turns out that these
slopes
would actually all stay the same
but they would just run for long
because the like you know the
segment to the right of the
bottom instead of going from 85
to 90 it would go from 80 to 90
do you see what I mean yeah the
height would change in
a way that I'm about to explain
okay so the thing I wanted to
get at is C
chapter 1.3
for details of
proof.
But a key ingredient is this.
The slope
has
this cool formula,
which is again derived in the
notes.
The denominator is n, the number
of data points.
The numerator is the number of
data points to the left of w
minus the number of data points
to the right of w.
And this is only defined,
as I said earlier,
when w is not equal to any of
the yi's.
Because when w is equal to any
of the yi's, again, you have to
think back at that piecewise
linear graph,
you're at a bend,
the slope is not defined there.
Number to the left minus number
to the right over n.
So this formula will help you
reason about what the height of
this graph is at any point.
Okay, and this is the kind of
thing you're going to practice
with in tomorrow's lab and in
the upcoming homework.
But let me give you an example.
Why don't we consider here this
segment?
And I will highlight it in green
here.
What is the slope of this
segment between 61 and 72 on
this graph?
What is the slope of the green
line segment?
Gustavo.
It would be negative 4 over n.
And what is n here?
n would be 5,
6.
Good.
How did you find that?
Because there was one point to
the left If you go to the center
and there's five points to the
right.
Remember,
the formula does not work when
you're exactly on a data point.
So you just consider an
arbitrary point on the segment.
So it could be anywhere here.
If you live here, how many data
points are to the left of you?
One.
How many are to the right?
Five.
And how many are there total?
Six.
So I have 1 minus 5 over 6,
which is negative 2 thirds.
What this shows you is anytime
you're left of the median, then
the number of data points to the
left of you is going to be less
than the number to the right.
You're less than halfway through
the distribution,
so you're going to have less to
the left, and so the slope is
negative.
As soon as you're halfway
through the data set,
you're going to have more to the
left, because you will have
passed more of the data set.
So left minus right will be
positive, and your slope will be
positive.
And that's how we reason about
the median being the minimizer,
because it's that point at which
you you go from having a
negative slope to a positive
slope.
OK?
Now, I'll also say,
your takeaway from this picture
may be, OK, anytime there's an
even number of data points, that
means there's a flat bottom.
But that's not necessarily true.
Can you think of a situation
where there's an even number of
data points but there isn't a
flat region where the slope is
0?
Even number of data points, but
there isn't a flat region at the
bottom.
Any guesses?
Shunwei?
When there's only two middle
values are the same? Yeah, what
if the two middle values are the
same?
Then there's an even number of
data points, but there aren't
any data points in between them,
so you could still have that
hard corner.
And the type of thing you will
see as you practice exam
questions is,
well, what if there were 50
values that were all equal to
the median?
Then what would the slope to the
segment of the left of the
median be and to the right?
Those are the sorts of things
that you'll start to play around
with.
Sound good?
We have a grasp of what's going
on with this mean absolute error
stuff.
Give us a short break here to
test out the new attendance
system.
So I'm not,
at least for today,
we're not going to use Poll
Everywhere.
Instead go to the course website
and in the top right
it'll say lecture attendance and
that should open a Google form.
What I want you to do is fill
out that Google form instead.
You have to be logged into your
U of M email to do this.
I'll show you if you go here.
Course website, top right,
says Attendance.
Give you another minute or so.
By the way, when you write what
is the most confusing aspect of
lecture, I read those responses.
So make sure to put something if
you're thinking about it.
A couple of people are asking
where did the formula for left
minus right over n come from.
Again,
read the course notes for that.
There are more details there,
and that is how we find that the
median minimizes mean absolute
error.
Yes, and remind me of your name.
Tiago.
Tiago, right.
I'm going to have to know how to
derive that equation for the
test, or is it just good to
know?
On an exam, I wouldn't ask where
that comes from for mean
absolute error specifically, but
you do need to know the slope
formula and the formula itself
and how it works,
but not where it comes from.
But the kind of thing you will
see on exams, but you're going
to practice with this in lab
homework,
is here's some other loss
function
where the calculus is a little
more easy.
Find the minimizer.
I'll give you another minute.
Yes?
So that's the two numbers
between the two mediums,
always have the same R absolute?
Yes.
It's like, if there are two
middle values, it will always be
flat in their output.
Like their mean absolute error
value will be the same.
If there are two values at the
middle,
yes.
Everyone checked in?
Anyone still working on it?
All good?
All right.
Close the form.
Thank you for five seconds.
We're going to let you start
working on it.
All right,
let's turn to the mic.
We could start in another
minute.
Just stretch your legs, chat,
drink water.
Let's see,
let's see, let's see, I have a
classroom.
Jeez.
I forgot to tell you all, so I
mean on Thursday we had the
tornado warning It was way later
in the day, so it didn't affect
us.
But when I was teaching my
central campus math class,
that amber alert thing came in
the middle of lecture.
We were in Angel Hall, in one of
those rooms that's the ground
floor, which is kind of a
basement,
kind of not.
But it had windows.
And so I'm in the middle of
class, and then everyone's phone
goes off.
I'm like, what's going on?
And we're deciding what to do.
And at first, I'm like, we're
underground.
It's fine.
We could keep doing class.
But there was just too much
chaos.
So I was like, whatever.
Let's just end class 15 minutes
early.
But then they wouldn't let
anyone leave the building.
I don't know if you were on
central campus then.
But at least in Angel Hall, they
weren't letting people leave.
And so we all just sat on the
ground of the building.
We basically just did office
hours like in the hallway for 20
minutes just sitting out there.
It was kind of fun,
but it was chaotic.
All right, let's get started.
So one of the takeaways you
should have seen here,
and I don't know if I did a good
enough job of making this super
clear,
is that depending on the loss
function and you choose,
you end up getting
different optimal parameters
that perhaps have different
behaviors.
So when we're working with the
constant model and choose
squared loss,
the optimal parameter,
which is the same as the optimal
prediction here, because our
parameter is our prediction with
the constant model,
is the average of all of our y
values, or the mean.
If we use absolute loss, then
the optimal parameter is the
median.
And what I want to talk about is
how the mean Mean and median are
different in ways that you've
already studied.
But I want to convey how those
are a byproduct of their
relationship to the squared loss
and absolute loss.
What is something you knew about
with regards to the mean and
median before this class?
How are the mean and median
different?
What's that about?
With the median,
outliers usually have less of an
effect on the value.
Awesome.
That's exactly what I was
getting at.
So what I've drawn here is a
histogram of the commute times
data set.
Now, this is different than the
graphs we saw before, because
the graphs we saw before,
we drew a scatter plot, And each
point conveyed both an
x amount and a y amount.
The x amount was the time we
left in the morning, and the y
amount was the amount of time it
actually took to get to work,
the commute time.
Here what I'm looking at is just
the distribution of commute
times,
where taller bars represent
larger frequencies.
And what I've drawn in purple is
the median of the data set, and
in orange is the mean of the
data set.
The median is the point in the
data set at which half of the
data is to the left
and
half is to the right.
What that means is if there are
some outliers, whether they're
at 130 minutes or 1.3
million minutes.
It doesn't change the median,
because the median is just where
half of the data is to the left
and half is to the right.
But you can imagine,
because of how the mean is
calculated, you have to add up
every single y-value and divide
by n.
If even one of them is a massive
outlier,
it drives up the entire mean,
okay? So when you look at
distributions like this,
the mean gets pulled in the
direction of the outliers,
whether they are big outliers or
small outliers, like you could
take a mirror image of this
graph and have most of the
values be to the right with some
outliers to the left and the
mean gets dragged by those
outliers.
Now this distribution here is
what I would call right skewed.
But that term, like I didn't
invent the term, but it's a
little confusing because the
data is to the left, even though
it's called right skewed.
The way I think about this is
imagine this was a dog or a cat,
whatever you prefer,
Its tail would be here, and
another term they use in
statistics for distribution is,
you could call this
right-tailed.
And the skew and the tail are
the same.
It's right-skewed or
right-tailed, but the data is to
the left.
In right-skewed data, the mean
is typically larger than the
median.
In left-skewed data, the mean is
less than the median.
and in data sets that are
symmetric, then the mean and
median are typically close.
What is a common example of
real-world data
that looks like this?
Mean is much larger than the
median,
the default example you should
think of.
Caleb.
Income.
Yeah, income or net worth.
Most people make a relatively
low amount of money, but there
are the Jeff Bezoses and whoever
else of the world that drive up
those numbers, which is why
whenever you're looking at
information about a population,
to have a complete picture, it's
useful to know both the mean and
the median.
This is all stuff you already
knew.
But what I want to convey is
that this is actually related to
empirical risk minimization.
Or one way you can think about
this is as a result of empirical
risk minimization.
Let me draw a picture for you.
And to be clear here, we're
comparing absolute versus
squared
loss.
Let's suppose we have a
hypothetical data set with just
four y values.
Or just they're y values, but
I'm drawing them on the x-axis
because it's easier to compare
them this way.
Okay,
1,
2,
3, and 14.
And let's consider the value
w equals 4.
The 14, this isn't really drawn
to scale, the 14 should look
further away.
So what are the squared losses
from w
equals 4,
like my candidate w, this w I'm
considering, to all four of my
data points?
What's the squared loss to the
data point 3?
Well, it's 1 squared, which is
1, to the data point 2.
Let me remove this a little.
Here I have the distance is 2
squared, which is 4.
Over here I have 3 squared,
which is 9.
And out here I have 10 squared,
which is 100.
So what is my mean squared
error?
Well, it's the average of 9,
4,
1, So that's up to 14 plus 100.
It's 114 over 4.
So it's like 28.5.
Now,
remember, our goal is to
minimize mean squared error or
mean whatever loss function
we're using.
Does w equals 4 minimize mean
squared error here?
You're saying no, it doesn't why
does it not?
You just know it doesn't but no
We just it just feels like it
shouldn't Sam Because the growth
how far it is is kind of
exponential.
So like if since quadratic it's
quadratic Yeah.
Since 14 is so far away, it's 10
away from 4.
That's the number one thing you
want to minimize.
Exactly.
So it's a little closer that
way.
So it's counterintuitive.
But the way to drive down the
mean squared error is actually
to move w closer to the outline.
And check out what happens when
we do that.
If I draw this graph again,
but with 1,
2,
3.
14,
but consider w equals 5 instead,
my 3 squared losses on the left
all go up.
Instead of 1,
I now have a 4.
Instead of a 4,
I now have a 9.
Instead of what used to be a 9,
I now have a 16.
and those three numbers are all
bigger than their old
counterparts do we agree this
used to be 9 now it's 16 this
used to be 4 now it's 9 this
used to be 1 now it's 4 seems
like things are just getting
worse but if you compare it to
what's going on on the right
what used to be 100
is now 81 and when you average
these four squared
losses,
4, 9, 16, and 81,
you actually get a smaller
number.
And so what I'm trying to convey
to
you is the behavior of the mean
is influenced by the fact that
it minimizes mean squared error.
And squared loss penalizes you
from being far away from these
outliers.
The way I think about it is that
these outliers have this sort of
like gravitational pull.
Like, I'm forcing you to be
close to me because if you're
not,
then your squared loss from me
will be super high,
which forces the predictions to
be skewed in that direction.
You see what I mean by that?
Whereas absolute loss,
the penalty of moving from w
equals 4 to w equals 5
hurts you three times as much on
the left, because you get one
unit further away from all three
things on the left and only one
unit closer to the thing on the
right.
So going from w equals 4 to w
equals 5 increases your
mean absolute error.
Okay, and we know from our
discussion of the median that
the best W if we were minimizing
mean absolute error isn't four
or five, it's anything between
two and three.
Right?
Do we agree with that?
But I'm saying with mean
absolute error going from W
equals four to W equals five
hertz,
you're getting further away on
average from the data.
But for mean squared error,
where the goal is to minimize
the average squared distance
from all the data points,
the fact that you have this one
outlier sort of skews your
parameters and or predictions
accordingly.
Do we see why that is?
OK,
so now we're looking at this in
the context of the constant
model,
but the fact that using squared
loss sort of pushes your
predictions in the direction of
outliers
is true with other models as
well,
including squared loss.
And this is actually a lab
question you will see tomorrow.
There will be a lab question
where there's a data set and two
lines.
One will say this is the line
that minimizes mean absolute
error.
One minimizes mean squared
And you have to think about
which one is which.
And the answer is that the one
that minimizes mean squared
error is the one that is pulled
more in the direction of the
outliers.
And it's because of this
behavior.
OK, in general,
squared loss is more influenced
by outliers.
Coming back here,
so squared loss is more
influenced by outliers than
absolute loss.
What if instead of squaring the
loss,
I raised it to the power of 4?
Well, what would you think would
happen?
Alex?
It would be the same effect,
but even way more extreme.
Exactly.
So now your distance from the
outliers is being penalized
quartically, which is the term
for degree four,
rather than quadratically.
What that means is your penalty
from being far away from an
outlier increases even more.
And so you can imagine the
outlier has even more of a pull.
What if you did degree 100 loss?
Then what?
I'm sort of baiting you into
predicting what the answer is
going to be.
Your guess is okay,
degree two you get pulled by the
outlier, degree four you get
pulled even more.
So maybe the picture you have in
your mind is degree four brings
you here,
and degree a million brings you
here.
That was my initial prediction
when I first started researching
this,
but that's not what happens.
Pretend you have degree a
million loss.
The optimal W isn't this,
but what do you think it is?
It's not the median, it's the
midpoint.
It's halfway between the
smallest and biggest data point.
Because if you think about what
degree 100 loss would be,
then your penalty for being far
away from anything is very high.
So if you overcorrect it and
say, OK, I'm just going to live
on w equals 14,
well, then think about how big
your loss to the data point one
would be.
So as that exponent gets bigger
and bigger,
the optimal parameter converges
to halfway between the min and
the max so that its worst case
distance to any point is
minimized.
Because if you're halfway
between the min and the max,
then that is the smallest worst
case distance you could have.
Because if you move away from
that, then the furthest you are
away from any data point
increases.
But if you're in the middle,
then while it's not necessarily
indicative of the data set,
you're not that far from the
smallest or the biggest.
But this is like a sort of
confusing idea, not something
that I've seen published or
anything like that anywhere.
This is more of like a research
idea, but it's like the kind of
thing you'll learn how to play
around with in lab tomorrow.
There is a question.
Sam, yeah.
Wait, would that be the,
are you saying that's the
optimal w?
The optimal w, if you use a
really high degree for your loss
function.
Remember, the loss function is
something that you pick in
advance.
If you use squared loss, the
optimal w is the mean.
If you use absolute loss, the
optimal w is the median.
I'm saying if you use degree 100
loss or degree a million loss,
the optimal w is halfway between
the min and the max.
What if there's like an infinite
amount of points on the left
side and there's like One point
that's all the way on the right
side That would still be true
for like L earlier for degree
100 or a million loss It may
just take higher degrees to get
to that convergence
Obviously doesn't matter for
quadratic or to power 400 or
whatever but does it ever matter
whether you're doing
No,
because if you're doing an odd
number you're supposed to
absolute value at first So if
you're doing like degree 3 or
degree 5 loss,
you'd take absolute value first
and then raise it to the
exponent because if you have an
odd number,
or sorry, you have an odd
degree,
a negative number to an odd
degree is still a negative
number, which is why you'd
absolute it first.
Yeah, good observation.
OK.
While we're here,
so we talked about that sort of
infinity behavior, which is
confusing.
Like I know it's hard to wrap
your head around.
Here's another
empirical risk function I want
you to think about.
Just the loss function part on
the right
is called zero-one loss.
And as the name suggests, it can
only be equal to one of two
things,
one if the prediction is wrong,
and zero if the prediction is
right.
So if we're concerned with
minimizing average zero-one
loss,
what do you think, and we're
using the constant model here,
what do you think the optimal w
is?
Brian.
The mode.
How'd you get that?
Just like when I have the most
amount directly on the point.
Exactly.
You can think of this loss
function as,
again, it only has two possible
values, 1 or 0.
And if the goal is to make the
average of the loss function as
small as possible,
that is, you want this entire
expression to be as small as
possible,
you want to trigger this 0.
Think of this as like a function
that's defined by an if
statement.
If y equals w,
return 0, otherwise return 1.
So what you want to do is
trigger the 0 case as often as
you can.
And how do you do that?
Well, you just pick w being
equal to the data point that was
most common without regards to
the shape of the distribution.
You just pick the one that's
most common.
And so you pick the data point
that's the mode.
Now, your question is, what if
there are multiple modes, or
what if every data point appears
exactly once?
Well then, there are multiple
minimizers for average 0, 1
loss.
My point in showing you this is
not that you need to sit and
memorize lots of different loss
functions, but it's to show you
that the loss function you
choose impacts the behavior of
the resulting predictions.
And things like the mean,
median, and mode, you've heard
about before, but they're
actually related to these ideas
of loss function, which I think
is interesting.
Questions with anything we've
done so far?
And I know we're moving quickly,
which is why,
even on the announcement slide
today, I said make sure to spend
some time reading through the
notes carefully.
Alex?
If each data point only appeared
once, would it even matter what
you choose for w for like the
minimum?
No,
it wouldn't.
They'd all have the same
minimizing
value of empirical risk.
To be clear, just because you
can use a loss function doesn't
mean you should.
What is important is to
understand how different loss
functions behave.
Sound reasonable?
What I want to give you now is
like a five minute preview of
the next thing we're going to
study.
You're going to play around with
this, especially in code,
including using scikit-learn,
which is like the industry
standard Python package for
non-neural network machine
learning.
You're going to see this in lab
tomorrow.
I want to give you a preview of
what that's going to look like.
And then on Thursday, we will
spend all our time discussing
the theory of it.
Remind me, what was the name of
the second model we said we
would study? We've sort of
talked in depth about the
constant model.
What was the next thing?
Paul?
Linear?
Yeah, the simple linear
regression model.
And simple just means it uses
one input variable or one
feature.
Later, we will learn about
multiple linear regression.
and that's when we use multiple
input variables.
So I'll say next model,
simple linear regression.
And as you can see,
and simple linear regression is
really just a rebranded y equals
mx plus b.
It's just that the slope now is
called w1, and the intercept is
now called w0.
And what I've shown you here are
three different possible
choices of intercepts and slopes
for this data set.
And the question is,
what is the most optimal
intercept and slope?
One thing you'll notice is that
the way in which we are making
our predictions,
now it includes the x's
themselves.
So for different times we leave
in the morning, we're getting
different predictions.
So with the constant model,
the parameter was the
prediction.
Like w star equals 50 means
we're just predicting 50 all the
time.
But here, finding that the slope
is equal to 100 or something
doesn't mean you're predicting
100.
It just means that's one of the
pieces of the formula you are
using to make your predictions.
And instead of finding just one
optimal parameter,
now we need to find an optimal
combination of parameters.
So what does the math for that
look like?
We're going to look at our
three-step recipe for empirical
risk minimization again.
The model we'll choose is the
simple linear regression
model.
We'll stick with squared loss,
though in the next homework you
will look at simple linear
regression and absolute loss.
And so what does the average
loss look like?
Well,
it should have a 1 over n and a
sum across all of our data
points.
Every average loss will have
this.
I'm going to have yi minus
something squared.
What is that something?
W0 plus w1 xi.
Great, and that difference is
being squared.
So I might still call this RSQ,
but this function now has how
many input variables?
Two, because there are two
parameters.
And so what we will look at next
class is how you find the
optimal combination of
parameters that minimizes this
function.
But to do that, we will need to
introduce basic ideas from
multivariable calculus,
calc 3,
because we now don't just have a
single variable along which we
take a derivative.
We have two variables and so we
have to take what are called
partial derivatives.
And just so you have it written
down,
I'll give you some of the
optimal
formulas.
But right away you're seeing
that this is a little different
than before because an x appears
in the formula,
which we should expect it to,
right? And it would be weird if
the formula for the optimal
slope
didn't involve the x-axis
component.
So this is the optimal slope,
w1 star and w0 star.
You see it is defined in terms
of the optimal slope.
You find the optimal slope
first, and then use it to find
the optimal intercept.
And the last thing I'll see
here,
and you don't really need to
rush to write this down because
it's all in the notes, of
course.
But you may want to refer to it
in tomorrow's lab.
For the optimal slope, there are
lots of equivalent
formulas.
So this is just one formula for
the optimal slope, but I will
show you a few others when we
come back on Thursday.
And when you're working on
homework problems, is the one
that you use depends on what the
question is asking you.
Depending on what the question
is asking you,
certain formulas may make it
easier or harder to do the math.
OK?
But like I said, you're going to
play around with these formulas
in tomorrow's lab.
That's it for today.
Thursday will be all about
simple linear regression.
And like I said, I have office
hours after this if you'd like
to ask anything.
I just did not want to get a
book again, oh my gosh, am I to
be able to decipher it?
I think they'll be just like
pulling me out of behind and
taking me by.
I think they'll be just like the
parts that we eat.
I think they're like doing it
all day long.
Like Sunday and Monday.
I feel like they're doing it all
day long.
They can get out of here.
Sunday.
I'm a slow worker,
but I mean like the first two
problems,
the first one's welcome survey,
the programming, that's like my
favorite.
Check in, I asked you to reply
to me as well,
and you copied
ProfessorCeeCee.net
as well.
Check in for true, and instead I
got empty.true,
or something.
Sounds good.
Which one?
I think it was like Chris who
would be here somewhere.
I got all false at the time.
I'll be like for...
That would be really cool if
you'd get like this in the chat.
Is there a lecture on the same
topic? because it says mp.true
instead of true.
Oh, do you want me to help?
Like, I can look at it.
You might have a print
statement.
I don't think so.
Your exam is not up to speed.
Lectures aren't at the same
time.
They're probably both at the
same time.
You can't touch anything.
Yeah,
I got you.
If it's possible,
I doubt it.
And if there is a conflict,
we will report it.
Just put everything you know
about for me.
We have a big classroom now, but
I wouldn't really prefer it if
we can kind of stick to one
side.
Maybe everyone is over here,
move on this side, please.
We now have, I think, 98 seats
for 40 people,
so I want to talk to two
separate sections of the room,
really.
Thank
you
very
much.